Register of the Pierre F. Goodrich papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Pierre F. Goodrich papers
1950-1977
Goodrich, Pierre F. (Pierre Frist), 1894-1973.
88006
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, agenda, conference materials, memoranda, speeches, printed matter, and photographs related to activities of the Mont Pelerin Society, the nature of liberty, and laissez-faire economic theory.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
John Davenport papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Friedrich A. von Hayek papers, Hoover Institution Archives
W. H. (William Harold) Hutt papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Fritz Machlup papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Mont Pèlerin Society records, Hoover Institution Archives
Benjamin A. Rogge papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1894 Born, Winchester, Indiana
1916 A.B., Wabash College
1917-1918 Second lieutenant, United States Army
1920 LL.B., Harvard Law School
1920-1973 Practiced law
1935-1973 President and director, Indiana Telephone Corporation
1950s Established the Winchester Foundation and Thirty Five Twenty
1951 Became a member of the Mont Pelerin Society
1960-1973 Founder and chairman, Liberty Fund
1973 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Pierre Goodrich papers consist of Goodrich's files on the Mont Pelerin Society, an international group concerned with the nature of liberty and laissez-faire economic theory. Materials include correspondence, conference materials, agenda, memoranda, speeches, printed matter, and photographs.
Pierre Goodrich attended his first meeting of the Mont Pelerin Society in 1951 in Beauvallon, France. His files document his activities in the society through meeting materials and correspondence with members, including Mont Pelerin Society founders Friedrich A. von Hayek and Ludwig von Mises. The Hayek correspondence includes a discussion of The Constitution of Liberty, with Goodrich's comments on the work.
The collection also includes correspondence related to disagreements within the society, now known as the Hunold Affair, and photographs of Mont Pelerin Society members.
Mont Pèlerin Society.; Economic policy.; Laissez-faire.; Liberty.
- Mont Pelerin Society file
  - General, 1951-1974 (Folder 1: 1-4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes correspondence, meeting reports, conference programs, circulars, nominations for membership, and clippings
  - Correspondence, 1951-1977 (Box 1-2)
    - Ayau, Manuel F., 1968-1973 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Brandt, Karl, 1953-1962 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Crane, Jasper E., 1957-1958 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Davenport, John A., 1973 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Erhard, Ludwig, 1957-1977 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Fisher, Antony G. A., 1968 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Gandil, Christian, 1957-1962 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Grimes, William H., 1954 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Grosse-Schware, Clara, 1956-1963 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Haberler, Gottfried, 1965-1966 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Habsburg, Otto von, 1961-1966 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Hayek, Friedrich A. von
      - General, 1953-1973 (Folder 1: 16)
      - Manuscript correspondence, 1959-1960 (Folder 1: 17)
        Includes comments on The Constitution of Liberty and memorandum of a conversation with Hayek
    - Hoff, Trygve J. B., 1957-1978 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Hunold, Albert, 1955-1972 (Folder 1: 19-20)
    - Hutt, William Harold, 1960-1968 (Folder 1: 21)
    - Jitta, A. C. Joseph, 1951 (Folder 1: 22)
    - Leffson, Ulrich, 1968-1971 (Folder 1: 23)
    - Leoni, Bruno, 1961-1967 (Folder 1: 24)
    - Lunshof, H. A., 1954-1958 (Folder 1: 25)
    - Menendez, Emilio, 1959 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Mises, Ludwig von
      - General, 1952-1966 (Folder 1: 27)
        Includes memorandum on inflation by Ludwig von Mises
      - Human Action correspondence, 1963 (Folder 1: 28)
        Contains correspondence with Henry Regnery
    - Morley, Felix, 1951 (Folder 1: 29)
    - Nymeyer, Frederick, 1965-1972 (Folder 1: 30)
    - Powell, J. Enoch, 1969 (Folder 1: 31)
    - Rappard, William E., 1958 (Folder 1: 32)
    - Rueff, Jacques, 1968-1969 (Folder 1: 33)
    - Schoeck, Helmut, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 34)
    - Schwartz, George L., 1960-1962 (Folder 1: 35)
    - Read, Leonard E., 1959 (Folder 1: 36)
    - Roepke, Wilhelm, 1966 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Schmolders, Gunter, 1958-1959 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Shenoy, B. R., 1964-1970 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Suenson-Taylor, Alfred (Lord Grantchester), 1958-1959 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Suviranta, Bruno, 1958-1967 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Van Sickle, John V., 1950-1972 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Veit, Otto, 1965 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Velasco, Gustavo R., 1962-1971 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Hunold Affair file, 1960-1961 (Folder 2: 9)
    Originally titled "alley fight"
  - Meetings file, 1960-1974 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence and conference materials
    - Kassel, Germany, 1960 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Belgium, 1962 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Semmering, Austria, 1964 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Stresa, Italy, 1965 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Vichy, France, 1967 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Aviemore, Scotland, 1968 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Caracas, Venezuela, 1969 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Munich, Germany, 1970 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Brussels, Belgium, 1974 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Mises, Ludwig von file, 1961, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - 80th birthday, 1961 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Memorials, 1973-1975 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Photographs, 1968 and undated (Folder 2: 21)
  - Speeches and writings, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - "Why Liberty?", 1958-1959 (Folder 2: 22)
      Includes correspondence